Bayes Theorem can get a little more complex.
贝叶斯定理也能分析复杂情况
Let's take a look at a small example,
我们来看一个例子
and what we'll do here is we'll mess a bit with the prior probability.
这个例子和先验概率有关
So, again, we have Alex and Brenda in the office and we saw someone pass by quickly.
办公室里仍然有 Alex 和 Brenda 两个人 我们看到一人快速经过
And we don't know who the person is.
但不知道这个人是谁
So let's say we look more carefully at their schedules and we
所以我们仔细查阅了他们的工作时间表 然后发现
realize that Alex actually works from the office most of the time.
Alex 大部分时间在办公室工作
He comes by three days a week.
他每周有三天都在办公室
And Brenda travels a lot for work so
Brenda 经常出差
she actually comes to the office only one day a week.
她每周只有一天在办公室
So, initially, without knowing anything about the red sweater,
所以 首先 在没有红色毛衣这个前提条件下
all we know is that it's three times more likely to see Alex than to see Brenda.
我们推测 这个人是 Alex 的可能性是 Brenda 的三倍
Therefore, our prior probabilities are 0.75 for Alex and 0.25 for Brenda.
因此 Alex 的先验概率是 0.75 而 Brenda 是 0.25
And let's say that we have this happening throughout all the weeks.
我们假设连续几周都是这种情况
But now we use our extra knowledge,
但现在 根据我们的额外信息
which is that the person we saw had a red sweater.
我们看到的这个人穿着红色毛衣
The rule is still as before,
和之前一样
as Alex wears red twice a week,
Alex 每周有两次穿红色毛衣
and Brenda wears red three times a week.
Brenda 每周有三次穿红色毛衣
So, naively, we would think that the real probabilities are not exactly 0.75 or 0.25,
我们会自然地想到 真正的概率并不是 0.75 与 0.25
because Brenda wears a red sweater more than Alex.
因为 Brenda 每周比 Alex 多穿一次红色毛衣
So they should be a little closer to each other.
所以 二者的概率应该更接近一些
Let's calculate them. So, we'll do the following.
我们按下面的方式重新计算一下
Let's think of the columns as weeks instead.
以纵列为单位
So now, for each five-day work week,
所以 每周五天的工作日当中
Alex wears red twice and Brenda three times.
Alex 穿红色毛衣两次 Brenda 穿红色毛衣三次
So we color the days they wore red.
我们把他们穿红色毛衣的日期标红
Now, since we know the person wore red,
已知我们看到的这个人穿红色毛衣
we forget about the times that they didn't.
所以不考虑他们没有穿红色毛衣的时候
So, we have nine times someone wore red.
两人穿红色毛衣的次数共九次
Six of them are Alex,
其中六次是 Alex
and three of them are Brenda.
三次是 Brenda
Therefore, among nine times we saw someone wearing red,
因此 假设我们有九次看到有人穿红色毛衣快速经过
two thirds of the times it was Alex,
那么这个人是 Alex 的概率是三分之二
and one third of the time it was Brenda.
是 Brenda 的概率是三分之一
Thus, our posterior probabilities are two thirds,
因此 我们的后验概率就是 Alex 三分之二
or 0.67, for Alex,
也就是 0.67
and one third, or 0.33, for Brenda.
Brenda 三分之一 也就是 0.33
So, it looks like we did a little bit of magic.
看起来就像是我们变了个小魔术
Let's do this again in a more mathematical way.
我们用一种更数学的方式再来算一次
We saw a person,
我们在办公室看到一个人
and initially all we know is that it's Alex with
起初 我们推测这个人是 Alex 的可能性是 75%
a 75 percent probability and Brenda with a 25 percent probability,
是 Brenda 的可能性是 25%
since Alex comes to the office three times a week and Brenda once a week.
因为 Alex 每周去办公室三次 而 Brenda 每周只去办公室一次
But now new information comes to light,
现在又有了新的已知信息
which is that the person is wearing a red sweater,
我们看到的这个人穿着红色毛衣
and the data says that Alex wears red two times a week.
数据显示 Alex 每周穿两次红色毛衣
So, now we look at Alex.
下面 我们先来分析 Alex
What is the probability that he's wearing red?
这个穿红色毛衣的人是 Alex 的可能性是多少呢？
Since the work week has five days and the probability of him wearing red is two fifths,
因为每周有五个工作日 她穿红色毛衣上班的概率是五分之二 也就是 0.4
or 0.4 and the probability of him not wearing red is the complement, so 0.6.
那么她没有穿红色毛衣去上班的概率就是补数 也就是0.6
Same thing with Brenda. Since she wears red three times a week,
Brenda 也是同样的道理 因为她每周穿三次红色毛衣
then the probability of her wearing red today is 0.6,
所以她今天穿红色毛衣的概率就是 0.6
and the probability of her not wearing red is 0.4.
没有穿红色毛衣的概率就是 0.4
Now, by the formula of conditional probability,
根据条件概率的公式
the probability that these two will happen is the product of the two probabilities,
这两种情况发生的概率就是两个事件概率的乘积
p of Alex, times p of red given Alex.
这个人是 Alex 的概率乘以 Alex 穿红色毛衣的概率
Therefore, the probability of the person we saw is Alex, and that they're wearing red,
所以 我们看到的这个人是 Alex 而她恰好穿红色毛衣的概率
is precisely 0.75 times 0.4.
就是 0.75*0.4
We multiply them and put the result here.
二者相乘 得到乘积
We calculate the other probabilities in the same way.
用同样的方式计算其他情况的概率
The probability of the person we saw is Alex and that he's not
我们看到的这个人是 Alex 而她没穿红色毛衣的概率
wearing red is 0.75 times 0.6.
就是 0.75*0.6
The probability that the person we saw is Brenda and that
我们看到的这个人是 Brenda 而她恰好穿红色毛衣的概率
she's wearing red is again the product of these probabilities,
也是两个概率的乘积
which is 0.25 times 0.6.
也就是 0.25*0.6
And finally, the probably of the person we saw is Brenda and that she's
最后一种情况 我们看到的这个人是 Brenda 而她没有穿红色毛衣的概率
not wearing red is 0.25 times 0.4.
就是 0.25*0.4
And now here's where the Bayesian magic happens. Are you ready?
接下来就是使用贝叶斯定理的时候了
We have four possible scenarios,
我们分析 共有四种可能的情况
and you can check that these four probabilities add to one.
你也可以验证一下 这四种情况的概率相加应等于一
But we know one thing,
但有一点我们可以确定
that the person we saw was wearing red.
我们看到的这个人穿着红色毛衣
Therefore, out of these four scenarios,
所以 在这四种情况中
only two are plausible,
只有两种情况符合条件
the two when the person is wearing red.
就是当 Alex 或者 Brenda 穿红色毛衣的时候
So, we forget about the other two.
所以 我们不考虑另外两种情况
Now, since our new universe consists of only these two scenarios,
鉴于现在一共只有两种情况了
then the probabilities should be higher.
二者的概率应该更高
But the ratio should still be the same with respect to each other.
但比例应保持不变
This means we need to normalize them, or,
所以 我们要把它们归一化
equivalently, divide them by something so that they now add to 1.
用它们分别除以一个数 使结果相加等于1
The thing we should divide them by is the sum of the two.
这个数就是二者的总和
So our new probability of the person being Alex is the top one, namely,
所以 这个人是 Alex 的概率就是第一个等式
0.75 times 0.4, divided by the sum of the two,
0.75 乘以 0.4 再除以二者的总和
namely, 0.75 times 0.4,
也就是 0.75 乘 0.4
plus 0.25 times 0.6.
加上 0.25 乘 0.6
This is precisely two thirds, or 0.67.
结果恰好是三分之二 也就是 0.67
And now, we can see that the complement is the probability that the person is Brenda,
这个人是 Brenda 的概率恰好是它的补数
which is one third,or 0.33.
即三分之一 也就是 0.33
If we take Brenda's probability and divide it by the sum of both probabilities,
如果我们用上面的公式计算 Brenda 的概率
we can see that we get one third, as desired.
结果同样是三分之一
And that's it. That is Bayes theorem at its full potential.
这就是贝叶斯定理的真正魔力